Guide to the Abraham Hayward correspondence files: 1063 items, 1790-1889
The New York Public Library. Carl H. Pforzheimer Collection of Shelley and His Circle.
Abraham Hayward correspondence files: 1063 items
1790-1889
Pforz MS
19616
Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884
The New York Public Library. Carl H. Pforzheimer Collection of Shelley and His Circle. Stephen A. Schwarzman Building Fifth Avenue at 42nd Street, New York, NY 10018-2788
1063 items
Abraham Hayward, English essayist and translator. His many friendships with significant figures in the literary and political circles of Victorian London resulted in this collection of correspondence. The Abraham Hayward Correspondence Files are chiefly comprised of letters addressed to Abraham Hayward by various English writers, politicians and society figures between 1831 and 1884. Among the correspondents represented are: Lord Brougham, lord chancellor; John Wilson Croker, politician and writer; Isaac D'Israeli, writer; W. E. Gladstone, prime minister and author; Letitia Elizabeth Landon, poet; Edward Bulwer-Lytton, writer and politician; Lady Sydney (Owenson) Morgan, novelist and hostess; Count D'Orsay, man of fashion; Samuel Rogers, poet; and William Makepeace Thackeray, novelist. A few items in the Files are letters addressed to recipients other than Hayward, some apparently collected by him as autographs.
Abraham Hayward was born in 1801 in Wilton, near Salisbury. To study law at the Inner Temple, he moved in 1824 to London, where he remained for the rest of his life. As a member of the London Debating Society, the young Hayward proved his skill for oratory in debates against such opponents as John Stuart Mill. In 1828 he became joint editor of Law Magazine, or, Quarterly Review of Jurisprudence, and was called to the bar in 1832. The following year he published his translation of Goethe's Faust, which earned wide acclaim and made him part of fashionable society both in Germany and at home. Though ought the rest of his life Hayward was a prolific writer of journal articles on various topics. Though he never himself achieved real fame, he counted many celebrities among his friends.
Now housed in archival sleeves within upright storage boxes, the letters originally came to the Pforzheimer Collection wrapped in ten bundles of roughly one hundred letters per bundle, each tied with pink tape (see picture to right). The significance of the bundled groupings remains unknown, but the arrangement was likely done by Henry E. Carlisle in preparation for his 1886 edition of selected Hayward letters. The original bundle numbers and ordering are recorded in each item's call numbers. The two digits immediately following HWD in the call number represent the original bundle number; the three further digits reflects the ordering within each bundle. Items with a call number stem other than HWD have been separated from the Files and integrated with other Pforzheimer manuscripts. Their original bundle and order numbers are unknown.
The majority of the over one-thousand manuscripts included in the Abraham Hayward Correspondence Files are letters addressed to Hayward by various English writers, politicians and socialites from between the years 1831 and 1884. While they constituted a portion of the materials used to produce Henry E. Carlisle's 1886 Selection from the Correspondence of Abraham Hayward, only a few letters from the Pforzheimer Collection's Hayward Files were included in that publication; most letters remain unpublished.
As the Pforzheimer Collection is primarily a repository for Romantic studies, the Hayward Files were originally of interest to the Pforzheimer Collection for the one letter contained in them by Mary Shelley. For Victorian scholars, however, the Hayward Files provide a substantial resource for research in politics, publishing and fashionable society life. Among the diverse correspondents represented are: Lord Brougham, lord chancellor; John Wilson Croker, politician and writer; Isaac D'Israeli, writer; W. E. Gladstone, prime minister and author; Letitia Elizabeth Landon, poet; Edward Bulwer-Lytton, writer and politician; Lady Morgan, novelist and hostess; Count D'Orsay, man of fashion; Samuel Rogers, poet; and William Makepeace Thackeray, novelist. A few items in the Files are letters addressed to recipients other than Hayward, some apparently collected by him as autographs.
In addition to the Abraham Hayward Correspondence Files, the Pforzheimer Collection also holds a copy of a memo from Lady Byron to Harriet Beecher Stowe, in Hayward's hand, on the Byron marriage and separation (B'ANA 0061); and a letter from Hayward to the novelist Jane Porter. For further details on these holdings, see the catalog record for the Abraham Hayward Manuscript Material.
Also held is Hayward's personal bound volume collecting articles written by himself, clipped from the Quarterly Review and the Edinburgh Review. The table of contents is written in ink, in Hayward's hand. Other Hayward-related printed materials held by the Pforzheimer Collection include the 1890 Sotheby catalog of his library; a copy of the first (1858) edition of his Biographical and Critical Essays; his 1870 article for the Quarterly Review on Harriet Beecher Stowe's Lady Byron Vindicated; his 1880 Sketches of Eminent Statesmen; and Henry E. Carlisle's 1886 Selection from the Correspondence of Abraham Hayward.
Aberdare, Henry Austin Bruce, Baron, 1815-1895; Aberdeen, George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of, 1784-1860; Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Baron, 1834-1902; Agar, James Charles Herbert Welbore Ellis, Earl of Normanton, 1818-1896; Aikin, John, 1747-1822; Airey, Richard, 1803-1881; Airlie, David Graham Drummond Ogilvy, Earl of, 1826-1881; Alderson, Mildred Anne Cradock-Hartopp Scott, d. 1909; Amherst of Arracan, William Pitt Amherst, Earl, 1773-1857; Ashley, Evelyn, 1836-1907; Baines, Thomas, 1806-1881; Baring, Thomas, Sir, 1772-1848; Barrington, George William Barrington, Viscount, 1824-1886; Beauchamp, Mary Catherine Stanhope, Countess, 1844-1876; Beauvale, Alexandrina Julia Theresa Wilhelmina Sophia (Adine) von Maltzahn, Baroness, 1818-1894; Bedford, Francis Charles Hastings Russell, Duke of, 1819-1891; Benson, Christopher, 1788-1868; Bentley, George, 1828-1895; Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James Beresford), 1820-1887; Bernal-Osborne, Catherine Isabella, d. 1880; Bernstorff, Anna, Countess; Bischoffsheim, Clarisse; Blackwood, John, 1818-1879; Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness; Blennerhassett, Mary Beatrice Armstrong; Brewster, A. (Abraham), 1796-1874; Brougham and Vaux, Henry Brougham, Baron, 1778-1868; Bulwer, Edward Earle Gascoyne, Sir, 1829-1910; Cadogan, F. W. (Frederick William), 1821-1904; Cardigan, Robert Brudenell, Earl of, 1760-1837; Cardwell, Edward Cardwell, Viscount, 1813-1886; Carnarvon, Evelyn Stanhope Herbert, Countess of, 1834-1875; Cary, Henry Francis, 1772-1844; Cavendish, 1831-1899; Chambers, Robert, 1802-1871; Charlemont, James Molyneux Caulfeild, Sir, Earl of, 1820-1892; Chatterton, Georgiana, Lady, 1806-1876; Childe, E. V. (Edward Vernon), 1804-1861; Chorley, Henry Fothergill, 1808-1872; Christie, William Dougal, 1816-1874; Clanricarde, Harriet Canning de Burgh, Marchioness of, 1804-1876; Clanricarde, Ulick John De-Burgh, Marquis of, 1802-1874; Clanwilliam, Richard Charles Francis Christian Meade, Earl of, 1795-1879; Clarendon, George William Frederick Villiers, Earl of, 1800-1870; Clay, James, 1804 or 5-1873; Clyde, Colin Campbell, Baron, 1792-1863; Cockburn, Alexander James Edmund, Sir, 1802-1880; Collier, John Payne, 1789-1883; Cook, John Douglas, 1808?-1868; Cookesley, W. G. (William Gifford), 1802-1880; Cornwallis-West, Mary, 1858-1920; Cowley, Olivia Cecilia Fitzgerald, Countess, 1807-1885; Croker, John Wilson, 1780-1857; Crowe, Eyre, 1824-1910; Dalling and Bulwer, Henry Lytton Bulwer, Baron, 1801-1872; De Fonblanque, Ethel M; De La Warr, Charles Richard Sackville-West, Earl, 1815-1873; De Morgan, Augustus, 1806-1871; Delane, John Thaddeus, 1817-1879; Denman, George, 1819-1896; Denman, Thomas Denman, Baron, 1779-1854; Derby, Constance Villiers Stanley, ountess of, 1840-1922; Devonshire, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1808-1891; Dick, Quintin, 1777-1858; Disraeli, Isaac, 1766-1848; Doherty, John, 1783-1850; Donoughmore of Knocklofty, Thomasina Jocelyn Steele Hutchinson, Countess of, d. 1890; Douglas, David, 1823-1916; Doyle, Francis Hastings, Sir, 1810-1888; Drummond, Henry, 1786-1860; Duff Gordon, Lucie, Lady, 1821-1869; Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood, Marquis of, 1826-1902; Dufferin and Clandeboye, Helen Selina Blackwood, Baroness, 1807-1867; Dukinfield, Henry Robert, Sir, 1791-1858; Dunlop, Alexander Graham, 1814-1892; Dyce Sombré, Mary Anne Jervis, 1812-1893; Elcho, Francis Wemyss-Charteris Douglas, Lord, 1818-1914; Elliot, Elizabeth Howe Bromley, 1824?-1880; Elliot, Frances, 1820-1898; Ellis, Henry, Sir, 1777-1869; Elwin, Whitwell, 1816-1900; Erle, William, Sir, 1793-1880; Escott, T. H. S. (Thomas Hay Sweet), 1844-1924; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865; Falkland, Lucius Bentinck Cary, Viscount, 1803-1884; Fane, Violet, 1843-1905; Ferguson, Robert, 1799-1865; Finlason, W. F. (William Francis), 1818-1895; Follett, William Webb, Sir, 1798-1845; Fonblanque, Albany, 1793-1872; Ford, Richard, 1796-1858; Forster, W. E. (William Edward), 1818-1886; Galton, Francis, 1822-1911; Galton, Mary Anne Nicholson Douglas; Gayangos, Pascual de, 1809-1897; Gibson, S. A. Milner (Susannah Arethusa Milner), 1814-1885; Gladstone, W. E. (William Ewart), 1809-1898; Glenesk, Algernon Borthwick, Baron, 1830-1908; Goulburn, Edward, 1787-1868; Graham, James, Sir, 1792-1861; Grant Duff, Mountstuart E. (Mountstuart Elphinstone), Sir, 1829-1906; Granville, Castalia Rosalind, Countess, 1847-1938; Granville, Granville George Leveson-Gower, Earl, 1815-1891; Greenwood, Frederick, 1830-1909; Greville, Charles, 1794-1865; Grote, Harriet, 1792-1878; Grote, Mary A. E; Gurney, Russell, 1804-1878; Halifax of Monk Bretton, Mary Gray Wood, Viscountess, d. 1884; Halifax, Charles Wood, Viscount, 1800-1885; Hallam, Henry, 1777-1859; Harrington, Leicester Stanhope, Earl of, 1784-1862; Hatherley, William Page Wood, Baron, 1801-1881; Hawtrey, Edward Craven, 1789-1862; Hayter, William Goodenough, Sir, 1792-1878; Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884; Herbert of Lea, Sidney Herbert, Baron, 1810-1861; Herbert, Mary Elizabeth Herbert, Baroness, 1822-1911; Holland, Henry Richard Vassall, Baron, 1773-1840; Holland, Mary Augusta Coventry Fox, Baroness, 1812-1889; Hook, Theodore Edward, 1788-1841; Howden, John Hobart Caradoc, Baron, 1799-1873; Jameson, Mrs. (Anna), 1794-1860; Kilbracken, Arthur Godley, Baron, 1847-1932; Kimberley, John Wodehouse, Earl of, 1826-1902; Kinglake, Alexander William, 1809-1891; Kingsdown, Thomas Pemberton-Leigh, Baron, 1793-1867; L. E. L. (Letitia Elizabeth Landon), 1802-1838; Lamington, Alexander Dundas Ross Wishart Cochrane-Baillie, Baron, 1816-1890; Landseer, Edwin Henry, Sir, 1802-1873; Landseer, John George, 1763 or 69-1852; Lansdowne, Henry Petty-Fitzmaurice, Marquess of, 1780-1863; Lardner, Dionysius, 1793-1859; Lawson, Wilfrid, Sir, 1829-1906; Le Flo, Adolphe, 1804-1887; Lennox, William Pitt, Lord, 1799-1881; Lewis, George Cornewall, Sir, 1806-1863; Lewis, Theresa, Lady, 1803-1865; Lightfoot, Joseph Barber, 1828-1889; Lisgar, John Young, Baron, 1807-1876; Locker-Lampson, Frederick, 1821-1895; Lowe, Georgiana Orred, d. 1884; Lowry-Corry, Alice Margaret Greg, d. 1932; Lyndhurst, Georgiana Goldsmith Copley, Baroness, 1807?-1901; Lyndhurst, John Singleton Copley, Baron, 1772-1863; Lyons, Richard Bickerton Pemell Lyons, Earl, 1817-1887; Lysons, Samuel, 1806-1877; Lyttelton, George William Lyttelton, Baron, 1817-1876; Lytton, Edward Bulwer Lytton, Baron, 1803-1873; Mackenzie, G. Muir (Georgina Muir), d. 1874; Mackintosh, James, Sir, 1765-1832; Maclean, Charles Hope; Macpherson, W; Macready, William Charles, 1793-1873; Malcolm, George, Sir, 1818-1897; Manchester, William Drogo Montagu, Duke of, 1823-1890; Manners, John, Lady; Manning, Henry Edward, 1808-1892; Marie, Princess of Lichetenstein, 1850-1878; Markham, John, Captain, b. 1797; May, Thomas Erskine, 1815-1886; Merivale, Herman, 1806-1874; Meves, Augustus; Minto, Emma Elliot-Murray-Kynynmound, Countess of, d. 1882; Mitford, Mary Russell, 1787-1855; Mohl, Mary Clarke, 1793-1883; Moira, John Rawdon, Earl of, 1720-1793; Molesworth, William, Sir, 1810-1855; Molíns, María del Carmen de Aguirre-Solarte y Alcíbar, Marquesa de; Monck, Charles Stanley Monck, Viscount, 1819-1894; Morgan, Lady (Sydney), 1783-1859; Morgan, Thomas Charles, Sir, 1783-1843; Morley, John, 1838-1923; Mortlock, Ethel; Mount-Temple, William Francis Cowper-Temple, Baron, 1811-1888; Mundy, Godfrey Charles, 1804-1860; Napier, Macvey, 1776-1847; Newcastle, Henry Pelham, Duke of, 1811-1864; Northbrook, Thomas George Baring, Earl of, 1826-1904; O'Neill, Eliza, 1791-1872; Ormathwaite, John Benn Walsh, Baron, 1798-1881; Orsay, Alfred Guillaume Gabriel, comte d', 1801-1852; Osborne, Ralph, 1808-1882; Osborne, W. G. (William Godolphin), 1804-1899; Paget, James, Sir, 1814-1899; Palmerston, Emily Lamb, Viscountess, 1787-1869; Peel, Adelaide Dugdale, d. 1890; Peel, Laurence, 1801-1888; Peel, Robert, Sir, 1822-1895; Pell, Alfred; Phillpotts, Henry, 1778-1869; Pigot, David Richard, 1797-1873; Planché, J. R. (James Robinson), 1796-1880; Platt, Thomas Joshua, Sir, 1788 or 90-1862; Pollington, Venetia; Pollock, F. (Frederick), Sir, 1783-1870; Ponsonby, Henry Frederick, Sir, 1825-1895; Portland, William John Cavendish-Scott-Bentinck, Duke of, 1800-1879; Power, Marguerite A., 1815?-1867; Procter, Anne Benson, 1799-1888; Rawlinson, Henry Creswicke, Sir, 1810-1895; Reay, Fanny Georgiana Jane Hasler, Baroness; Reeve, Henry, 1813-1895; Reid, Stuart J. (Stuart Johnson), 1848-1927; Rennell, James, 1742-1830; Rogers, Samuel, 1763-1855; Romilly, John Romilly, Baron, 1802-1874; Rose, George, Sir, 1782-1873; Rothschild, Anthony Nathan de, Sir, 1810-1876; Rothschild, Louisa Montefiore Rothschild, Baroness de, d. 1910; Rous, Henry John, 1795-1877; Russell, Arthur, 1825-1892; Russell, Laura, Lady, d. 1910; Rutland, John James Robert Manners, Duke of, 1818-1906; Sackville, Lionel Sackville Sackville-West, Baron, 1827-1908; Salisbury, Georgina Charlotte Alderson Gascoyne-Cecil, Marchioness of, 1827-1899; Sandhurst, William Rose Mansfield, Baron, 1819-1876; Sandwith, Humphry, 1822-1881; Selborne, Maud, 1858-1950; Shaftesbury, Anthony Ashley Cooper, Earl of, 1801-1885; Shelley, Mary Wollstonecraft, 1797-1851; Sherbrooke, Robert Lowe, Viscount, 1811-1892; Sinclair, Tollemache, Sir, 1825-1912; Slidell, John, 1793-1871; Slidell, Marie Mathilde Deslonde; Smith, Rosalind, b. 1821; St. Albans, William Amelius Aubrey de Vere Beauclerk, Duke of, 1840-1898; St. Germans, Edward Granville Eliot, Earl of, 1798-1877; Stanhope, Emily Harriet Kerrison Stanhope, Countess, d. 1873; Stanhope, Philip Henry Stanhope, Earl, 1781-1855; Stanley of Alderley, Henrietta Maria Dillon-Lee Stanley, Baroness, 1807-1895; Stanley, Dorothy, Lady, d. 1926; Stephen, George, Sir, 1794-1879; Stewart-Mackenzie, Hannah Charlotte Hope-Vere, d. 1868; Stirling Maxwell, William, Sir, 1818-1878; Storks, Henry Knight, Sir, 1811-1874; Strangford, Emily Anne Beaufort Smythe, Viscountess, d. 1887; Strangford, George Augustus Frederick Percy Sydney Smythe, Viscount, 1818-1857; Strzelecki, Paul Edmund de, 1797-1873; Swinton, J. R. (James Rannie), 1816-1888; Tait, Archibald Campbell, 1811-1882; Thackeray, William Makepeace, 1811-1863; Tomline, George, 1813-1889; Torrington, George Byng, Viscount, 1812-1884; Trench, Richard Chenevix, 1807-1886; Truro, Thomas Wilde, Baron, 1782-1855; Tyndall, John, 1820-1893; Van de Weyer, Jean-Sylvain, 1802-1874; Ventry, Harriet Elizabeth Frances Wauchope, Baroness, 1828-1906; Villiers, Charles Pelham, 1802-1898; Vogue, Achille; Waldegrave, Frances Elizabeth Anne (Braham), Countess of, 1821-1879; Walpole, Spencer H. (Spencer Horatio), 1806-1898; Webb, Emilia Jane, 1826-1889; Westmorland, John Fane, Earl of, 1784-1859; Westmorland, Priscilla Anne Fane, Countess of, 1793-1879; Williams-Wynn, Marie Emily, d. 1905; Winchilsea, George James Finch-Hatton, Earl of, 1815-1887; Wortley, Jane Stuart, 1820-1900; Wyke, Charles Lennox, Sir, 1815-1897; Wynne, Mary Anne Frances Haggitt; Authors, English -- 19th century -- Correspondence; Politicians -- England -- 19th century -- Correspondence; Socialites -- England -- 19th century -- Correspondence; Hayward, Abraham: correspondence files
- Aberdare, Henry Austin Bruce, Baron, 1815-1895, Rangemore, Burton on Trent - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 6 November 1873; HWD 03.011; autograph letter signed
- Aberdeen, George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of, 1784-1860 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 26 July 1853; HWD 03.079; autograph letter signed
- Aberdeen, George Hamilton Gordon, Earl of, 1784-1860 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 26 January 1857; HWD 03.081; autograph letter signed
- Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Baron, 1834-1902, Athenaeum Club, Pall Mall - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 17 July 1876; HWD 10.053; autograph letter signed
- Acton, John Emerich Edward Dalberg Acton, Baron, 1834-1902, 72 Princes Gate - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 03.091; autograph letter signed
  with errata to some work.
- Agar, James Charles Herbert Welbore Ellis, Earl of Normanton, 1818-1896, Somerley, Ringwood - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 30 October 1875; HWD 01.031; autograph letter signed
- Aikin, John, 1747-1822 - to [?], HWD 08.016; autograph letter signed (fragment)
  addresses correspondent as "your Lordship".
- Airey, Richard, 1803-1881 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 24 June 1856; HWD 06.098; autograph letter signed
- Airey, Richard, 1803-1881, 19 South Street - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 06.096; autograph letter signed
- Airey, Richard, 1803-1881, 7, Lowndes Square. S. W - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 9 May 1878; HWD 07.025; autograph letter signed
- Airey, Richard, 1803-1881, 37 Grosvenor Place - to [?], 20 November 1886; HWD 08.058; autograph letter signed
- Airlie, David Graham Drummond Ogilvy, Earl of, 1826-1881 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 20 May 1868; HWD 03.004; autograph letter signed
- Alderson, Mildred Anne Cradock-Hartopp Scott, d. 1909, 97 Eaton Square - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 1 July [no year]; HWD 05.075; autograph letter signed
- Amherst of Arracan, William Pitt Amherst, Earl, 1773-1857, Montreal - to [Mr. Vulliamy], 13 January 1833; HWD 08.024; autograph letter signed
- Ashley, Evelyn, 1836-1907, 61 Cadogan Place - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 27 April 1871; HWD 03.074; autograph letter signed
- Baines, Thomas, 1806-1881 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 8 February 1854; HWD 03.064; autograph letter signed
- Baines, Thomas, 1806-1881, Lancaster - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 23 December 1848; HWD 02.081; autograph letter signed
- Baring, Thomas, 1799-1873 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, Friday 18 December [no year]; HWD 03.083; autograph letter signed
- Baring, Thomas, 1799-1873, Norman Court, Stockbridge - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 9 December 1869; HWD 03.084; autograph letter signed
- Baring, Thomas, Sir, 1772-1848, 1 December [no year]; HWD 06.104; autograph letter signed
- Barrington, George William Barrington, Viscount, 1824-1886, 19 Hertford Street, Mayfair, W - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, "Friday"; HWD 07.099; autograph letter signed
- Beauchamp, Mary Catherine Stanhope, Countess, 1844-1876 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 1868; HWD 06.009; autograph letter signed
- Beauvale, Alexandrina Julia Theresa Wilhelmina Sophia (Adine) von Maltzahn, Baroness, 1818-1894 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 30 December 1846; HWD 04.059; autograph letter signed
- Bedford, Francis Charles Hastings Russell, Duke of, 1819-1891, Woburn Abbey - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 31 January 1875; HWD 03.005; autograph letter signed
- Benson, Christopher, 1788-1868 - to Devonshire, William Cavendish, Duke of, 1808-1891, HWD 05.023; letter (copy)
  to "the Chancellor"; regarding a petition and the University of London.
- Bentley, George, 1828-1895, 8, New Burlington Street, London. W - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 27 November 1883; HWD 05.061; autograph letter signed
- Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James Beresford), 1820-1887, Arklow House, Connaught Place - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 14 June 1864; HWD 06.088; autograph letter signed
- Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James Beresford), 1820-1887, Bedgebury Park, Cranbrook - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 9 June 1868; HWD 02.072; autograph letter signed
- Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James Beresford), 1820-1887, Arklow House, Connaught Place W - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 29 July 1872; HWD 10.048; autograph letter signed
- Beresford Hope, A. J. B. (Alexander James), Arklow House, - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 17 June 1864; HWD 10.045; autograph letter signed
- Bernal-Osborne, Catherine Isabella, d. 1880 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 30 October [no year]; HWD 09.044; autograph letter signed
- Bernal-Osborne, Catherine Isabella, d. 1880, 8 Eccleston St, Chester Square - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 07.084; autograph letter signed
  "Catherine Isabella" stamped on stationery; July 1847.
- Bernstorff, Anna, Countess - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, [circa 1871-1873]; MISC 3515 b; printed invitation with name and date in manuscript
- Bernstorff, Anna, Countess, Prussia House - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 22 September [circa 1871-1873]; MISC 3515 a; autograph letter signed
- Bischoffsheim, Clarisse, Bute House, South Audley Street W - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, "Sunday"; HWD 07.076; autograph letter signed
- Blackwood, John, 1818-1879 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 19 May 1862; HWD 04.055; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 01.082; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 01.079; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 10 October 1883; HWD 01.080; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, Paris - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 30 October 1862; HWD 02.077; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, Paris - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 9 January 1863; HWD 01.081; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, Vienna - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 24 June 1863; HWD 01.083; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, Chateau du Plessis - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 15 September 1867; HWD 01.084; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, 11 Portugal St - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 3 July 1862; HWD 08.002; autograph letter signed
- Blaze de Bury, Marie, Baroness, Paris - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 7 January 1873; HWD 01.078; autograph letter signed
- Blennerhassett, Mary Beatrice Armstrong - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, HWD 04.081; autograph letter signed
- Brewster, A. (Abraham), 1796-1874, Fort Augustus - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 11 September 1853; HWD 01.073; autograph letter signed
- Brewster, A. (Abraham), 1796-1874 - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 25 July 1854; HWD 06.099; autograph letter signed
- Brewster, A. (Abraham), 1796-1874, Merrion Sq - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 19 July 1853; HWD 05.057; autograph letter signed
- Brewster, A. (Abraham), 1796-1874, Merrion Square - to Hayward, A. (Abraham), 1801-1884, 26 May 1859; HWD 06.043; autograph letter signed